Murder, Conspiracy and the Masterpiece that Revealed the Truth
Nightwatching is a drama, history film directed by Peter Greenaway.
An extravagant, exotic and moving look at Rembrandt's romantic and professional life, and the
controversy he created by the identification of a murderer in the painting The Night Watch.
Rembrandt van Rijn, played by Martin Freeman.
Hendrickje, played by Emily Holmes.
Saskia, played by Eva Birthistle.
Geertje, played by Jodhi May.
Gerard Dou, played by Toby Jones.
Ferdinand Bol, played by Jonathan Holmes.
Nightwatching is a 2007 film about the artist Rembrandt and the
creation of his 1642 painting The Night Watch.
The film is directed by Peter Greenaway and stars Martin Freeman as Rembrandt, with Eva Birthistle as his wife Saskia van
Uylenburg, Jodhi May as his lover Geertje Dircx, and Emily Holmes as his other lover Hendrickje Stoffels.
Reinier van Brummelen is the director of photography.
James Willcock, known for his esoteric sets,  is the art director.
The film is described by co-producer Jean Labadie as "a return to the Greenaway of The Draughtsman's
Contract." It features Greenaway's trademark neoclassical compositions and graphic sexuality.
The music is by Włodek Pawlik.
The film premiered in competition, at the Venice Film Festival.
Nightwatching is the first feature in Greenaway's film series "Dutch
Masters", and was followed by Goltzius and the Pelican Company.
An associated work by the same director is the documentary film Rembrandt's J'Accuse (2008), in which Greenaway
addresses 34 "mysteries" associated with the painting, illustrated by scenes from the drama.
The film explores themes of painter, biography, rembrandt, drama.
The tone is emotional.